Selligman Family Papers ALBA.296
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Selligman Family Papers
1930s
1936-1937
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McDiarmid, Lucy
ALBA.296
3.5 Linear Feet 3 Record Cartons, 1 Oversize box
Joseph Selligman, Jr. (1916-1937) served as a solider in the British division of the International Brigade during the Spanish Civil War. He died in early 1937 after receiving a head wound in the battle of Jarama. Following his death, his family collected documents relating to the Spanish Civil War and the circumstances surrounding his death. This collection contains a large volume of correspondence, including letters between Joseph Selligman Jr. and his family from 1933-1936 and letters among family members regarding the circumstances of his death. The collection also contains copies of Selligman's academic and personal writings from Swarthmore College.
Historical/Biographical Note
Joseph Selligman Jr. was born on December 25, 1916 in Louisville Kentucky to Esther and Joseph Selligman. He was the second of three children; his elder sister Augusta was born in 1913, and his younger sister Lucy was born in 1920. His mother, the former Esther Rosenberg, taught kindergarten before her marriage to Joseph Selligman Sr. in 1909. His father worked as a lawyer in partnership with his brother Alfred and was also prominent in local politics.
Joseph Selligman Jr. attended Louisville Male High School for three and a half years, graduating early in 1933. He then enrolled in Swarthmore College, a Quaker school in Pennsylvania, at the age of 16 in the fall of 1933. At Swarthmore Selligman wrote for the school's literary magazine and later became the editor and served on the debate team. In the summer of 1935 Selligman also participated in a Quaker Peace Caravan in Iowa, which promoted peace and non-violent resistance along with other Swarthmore students. In October of his senior year Selligman applied to Harvard for graduate work in philosophy, but in mid-December he left Swarthmore without his parents' knowledge and traveled to Europe to join the International Brigades fighting in the Spanish Civil War.
In an attempt to convince him to return Selligman's father sent his law partner, Joseph Everhart, to Paris, where he had last been heard from. By the time Everhart arrived, however, Selligman had already left for Spain. In Europe, Selligman initially tried to enlist under his own name but was rejected because he was only nineteen years old. He instead enlisted in a British battalion under the name Frank Neary, who was a young Irishman who sold his enlistment papers to Selligman after changing his mind about going to war.
Selligman entered Spain sometime in late December or early January. By mid-February he was fighting with a British battalion of the International Brigade along the Jarama River. At the battle of Jarama he suffered a head wound and was evacuated to a hospital near Madrid where he died two weeks later. His family believes he was the first American casualty of the Spanish Civil War.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to Joseph Sellingman, Jr. and his participation in the Spanish Civil War as a solider in the International Brigades. It is comprised of materials created by Selligman before he joined the war as well as many documents relating to his death in Spain in 1937. Documents in this collection include: college notebooks, essays, personal writings and poetry, publications from Swarthmore College, memorabilia, family correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, personal items, photographs, and foreign newspapers.
It also contains a large amount of correspondence relating the events surrounding his departure to Spain and his death. The collection also contains personal correspondence with important figures of the time such as the British Communist leader Harry Pollitt and the American journalist Martha Gellhorn and various members of the American diplomatic corps.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in a single series which is housed in four boxes. Much of the correspondence has been placed in folders either thematically or by author. For the most part, folders have not been arranged systematically, rather they have been arranged as much as possible in relation to thier order within thier original boxes. Several newspapers are housed separately in an oversized flat box.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lucy McDiarmid sent a donation of family papers related to her brother's, Joseph Selligman, involvement in the Spanish Civil War in 2013. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2013.017 and 2013.023. An additional gift containing letters of condolences and correspondence from Joseph Selligman Jr. was donated in 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.001.
Appraisal
Several newspapers and clippings regarding the Spanish Civil War have been removed from this collection. The large majority of those clippings came from the Louisville Times and the Louisville Courier-Journal after the death of Joseph Selligman Jr. in 1937. Also removed from this collection were several empty envelopes that did not have corresponding letters, otherwise letters and the envelopes they came in were preserved.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Selligman, Joseph Jr.
- Caravan for Peace-Iowa, 1935 (Box 1)
- Assorted Clippings and Pamphlets, circa 1930-1935 (Box 1)
- Photo: Joseph Selligman Jr., circa Dec 1936 (Box 1)
- Notes: Attempts to secure return of Joseph Selligman Jr., Dec 1936 (Box 1)
- Timeline of Correspondence, Jan-Mar 1937 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: Freida Krichway of the Nation Associates to Joseph Selligman Sr., Jan 3, 1937 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: Charles E. Crane, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
- Swarthmore Manuscript, 1935-1937; 2 Folders (Box 1)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Writings, circa 1933-1936 (Box 1)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. College papers and miscellaneous writings, circa 1933-1936; 2 Folders (Box 1)
- Swarthmore Phoenix, 1933-1937; 2 Folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s death, 1937 (Box 1)
- Bound Volume: Correspondence regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s departure and death, Dec 1936-Mar 1937 (Box 1)
- Youth and Heroic Death, Undated (Box 1)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Memorial Materials, 1937 (Box 1)
- Foreign Newspapers, Jul-Aug 1936 (Box 1)
- Lucy Selligman Contacts Book, Undated (Box 1)
- Joesph Selligman's personal items from Swarthmore College, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
- Clipping: Regarding Joseph Selligman Jr. and Swarthmore Manuscript, Jun 5, 1935 (Box 2)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Address Book, Undated (Box 2)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Swarthmore College Notebook, circa 1933-1936 (Box 2)
- Swarthmore Manuscript, Jun 1936 (Box 2)
- Highland Echo, May 15, 1930 (Box 2)
- Louisville Male High School Yearbook, 1933 (Box 2)
- Stamp Collection, Undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Joseph Selligman Jr. at Camp Winnebago, Summer 1929 (Box 2)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Happiness Chart, 1934-1936 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Jr., Dec 1927-Dec 1936 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Laci Borbas to Joseph Selligman Jr., 1936 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman- Sympathy, Mar-Jun 1937; 4 Folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Selligman Family - Condolences, 1937; 2014.001; 2 Folders (Box 2)
- Thank You cards, Undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Esther Selligman to Augusta Selligman, Jan 14, 1937-Mar 17, 1937 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Lucy Selligman, 1937 (Box 2)
- Corresondence: Incoming to Wallace Selligman, 1937 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Mr. and Mrs. Bernard Selligman, Mar 1937 (Box 2)
- Clippings: Regarding death of Joseph Selligman Jr., Mar 1937 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Betty, 1937 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman, Jul 1937-1945 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Iowa Peace Caravan, 1935 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Jr. to his parents from the Iowa Peace Caravan, 1935 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Jr. to Monica Blessinger, 1935 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Between Havas News Service and Joseph Selligman Sr., 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s watch, April 7, 1937 (Box 3)
- Assorted items from Joseph Selligman Jr.'s suitcase, Undated (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming regarding departure of Joseph Selligman Jr., Dec 1936 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Sympathy regarding departure of Joseph Selligman Jr., Dec 1936 (Box 3)
- Telegrams and Cables, Dec 1936-Jan 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Everhart regarding departure of Joseph Selligman Jr., Dec 1936; 1 folder (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Jr. to his parents, Oct - Dec 1936; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Jr. Letters from Spain (Originals), 1936-1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming from Joseph Selligman Jr. (Copies typed by his mother), 1936-1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming from Joseph Selligman Jr. to his Parents (Copies), Dec 1936-Feb 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Phoebe Davis to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming from Joe's college friends to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman, Dec 1936-Jul 1937 (Box 3)
- Death Certificate and Family Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman regarding events of Joseph's death, 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Between Martin Hourian and Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Selligman, Aug-Dec 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming from Fritz Manheim and Rabbi Joseph Rauch regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s whereabouts in Europe, Dec 1936-1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Vincent Polo to Esther Selligman, Jan 1944 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman Sr. and Harry Pollitt, Mar-Apr 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Martha Gellhorn and Esther Selligman, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Sergeant Marquette and Esther Selligman, Jan 16, 1946; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s death in Spain, 1938 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Incoming from the President and Dean of Swarthmore College, 1935-1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Rachel C. Grober to Esther Selligman, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Courier-Journal to Joseph Selligman Sr., Mar 16, 1937 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Joseph Selligman and the Daily Worker, 1937 (Box 3)
- The Highland Echo: Dedication. Louisville, KY., 1942 (Box 3)
- Joseph Selligman Jr. Memorial Record, undated (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Condolence Telegrams, 1937; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- Flower cards and Condolences, 1937; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- List of Thank You cards to send, undated; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- "Red Pencil List", undated; 2014.001 (Box 3)
- Correspondence: Miscellaneous condolence letters, undated (Box 3)
- Copies of the Swarthmore Phoenix, Mar 23, 1937 (Box 3)
- Assorted clippings and writings, undated (Box 3)
- Assorted clippings regarding Joseph Selligman Jr.'s death, undated (Box 3)
- Assorted clippings: Spain, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
- Courage by J.M. Barrie (Box 3)
- The American Mercury, May 1939 (Box 3)
- Pamphlet: Catholics Speak for Spain, undated (Box 3)
- The Story of Ferdinand, by Munro Leaf, drawing by Robert Lawson, Sep 1936 (Box 3)
- Assorted Newspapers, 1937-1945 (Box 4)
- Panoramas, undated (Flat-file-folder 2, Tray 1)